<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rohan French: Logician at Large</title>
    <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Rohan French: Logician at Large</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2015 22:05:37 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://rohan-french.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>McGee on Necessitation and Conditional Proof</title>
      <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/rules-inference-proof/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2015 22:05:37 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/rules-inference-proof/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been taking great pleasure in reading &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/olehjortland/&#34;&gt;Ole Hjortland&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/colincaret/&#34;&gt;Colin Caret&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s recent edited
&lt;a href=&#34;http://ukcatalogue.oup.com/product/9780198715696.do&#34;&gt;collection of papers&lt;/a&gt; from the long running Arche &amp;lsquo;Foundations of Logical Consequence&amp;rsquo;
project. So far I&amp;rsquo;ve greatly enjoyed every paper in the collection. What I want to point out
here is a rather curious passage in Van McGee&amp;rsquo;s contribution &amp;ldquo;The Categoricity of Logic&amp;rdquo;.
After claiming that the meanings of the sentential-connectives are given by their natural
deduction rules McGee goes on to make the following, rather curious, comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In proposing this, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to go to the extreme of saying that any inferential system
whose methods of reasoning with the classical connectives don&amp;rsquo;t include the rules is deficient
or defective. Normal systems of modal logic include the rule of necessitation (From $\varphi$,
you may infer $\Box\varphi$). If they also included conditional proof, you could assume $\varphi$,
derive $\Box\varphi$ by necessitation, then discharge the assumption to derive the invalid
conclusion $(\varphi \supset \Box\varphi)$.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McGee then goes on to argue that this is not a problem, because the rules of normal systems of
modal logic are &amp;ldquo;intended to preserve modal validity&amp;rdquo;, while natural deduction rules like
conditional proof preserve &amp;lsquo;being entitled to accept&amp;rsquo; but not &amp;lsquo;modal validity&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few strange things going on in this passage. Firstly, we have a rather awkward
comparison of logical frameworks. Typical presentations of normal modal logics are in the
&lt;em&gt;FMLA&lt;/em&gt; framework&lt;span class=&#34;badge&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, where we convieve of logics
as consisting of sets of valid formulas closed under various rules. In this setting necessitation
is the closure condition which tells us that whenever $A$ is in the set (i.e. is a theorem of the
logic) then so is $\Box A$. In settings like this we cannot even talk about rules in the &lt;em&gt;SET-FMLA&lt;/em&gt;
framework like Conditional Proof. To do this we would need to consider appropriate consequence
relations for modal logics where we can properly ask about the status of rules like conditional
proof. Lifted to such a setting the rule of necessitation becomes the
rule which takes us from $\emptyset\vdash A$ to $\emptyset\vdash\Box A$ &amp;ndash; i.e. if $A$ follows from the empty
set of premises, then so does $\Box A$. This is because necessitation is (to use terminology
popularised by Timothy Smiley) a &lt;em&gt;rule of proof&lt;/em&gt;, telling us that if we have proved $A$
then we can conclude $\Box A$. By contrast conditional proof, the rule which takes us from
$\Gamma, A \vdash B$ to $\Gamma\vdash A\supset B$ is a &lt;em&gt;rule of inference&lt;/em&gt;, telling us that if
we can deduce $B$ on the basis of some assumptions along with $A$ then we can conclude $A\supset B$
on the basis of those assumptions. What McGee is appealing to in the above quotation, though, is
the rule which allows us to transition from $\Gamma\vdash A$ to $\Gamma\vdash\Box A$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is the most natural way of reading the above passage, and in this case our diagnosis
of the above &amp;lsquo;problem&amp;rsquo; is quite simple: there is none, any appearance to the contrary arising due
to a confusion between rules of inference and rules of proof. This is a somewhat under-recognised
distinction, in part due to the phenomena, pointed out in section 4 of Lloyd&amp;rsquo;s paper &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;Smiley&amp;rsquo;s Distinction
between Rules of Inference and Rules of Proof&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; &lt;span class=&#34;badge&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,  of logicians thinking in terms of undifferentiated
axiomatisations (where an axiomatisation consists solely of a collection of axioms and rules) rather
than dividing up our rules into rules of inference and rules of proof).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the only way to read
this passage, though. There are presentations of normal modal logic which are closed under
the rule McGee seems to have in mind in the above quotation. Fix on a class of modal frames
and understand a model as being a model on one of those frames and let us define the following
two notions of validity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;$\Gamma\vdash A$ is &lt;em&gt;locally valid&lt;/em&gt; iff, for all models, $A$ is true at a world if all the formulas in $\Gamma$ are true there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;$\Gamma\vdash A$ is &lt;em&gt;globally valid&lt;/em&gt; iff, for all models, $A$ is true at all worlds in the model if all the formulas in $\Gamma$ are true at all worlds in that model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So local consequence preserves truth at a point in a model, while global consequence preserves
being true throughout (i.e. at all worlds in) a model. Now the rule mentioned above which takes
us from $\Gamma\vdash A$ to $\Gamma\vdash \Box A$ is globally valid, but is not locally valid.
By contrast, conditional proof preserves local validity but not global validity. If we think
in terms of global validity then we can say a bit more about what McGee might have in mind by
&amp;lsquo;modal validity&amp;rsquo;: preservation of modal validity is just preservation of truth in all possible
worlds. Reading McGee in this way will make this passage come out true, but personally I&amp;rsquo;m dubious
about whether this is the intended reading of this passage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moral of the story here? People ought to be more attentive to the rule of inference/rule
of proof distinction. Also, comparing logics typically concieved of in different frameworks
can quite quickly get you into trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTES&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;
[1] &lt;a name=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The notion of &amp;lsquo;logical framework&amp;rsquo; which I have in mind, and the labels &lt;em&gt;FMLA&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;SET-FMLA&lt;/em&gt;
for particular logical frameworks is due to Lloyd Humberstone. More information on this (and much
more besides) at &lt;a href=&#34;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/connectives-logic/&#34;&gt;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/connectives-logic/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;a name=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;L. Humberstone, &amp;ldquo;Smiley&amp;rsquo;s Distinction
between Rules of Inference and Rules of Proof&amp;rdquo;, In T. J. Smiley, Jonathan Lear &amp;amp; Alex Oliver (eds.), &lt;em&gt;The Force of Argument: Essays in Honor of Timothy Smiley&lt;/em&gt;. Routledge 107&amp;ndash;126 (2010)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypersequent Calculi for Contingent Existence</title>
      <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/presentations/presentations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rohan-french.github.io/presentations/presentations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is well known that the most straightforward way of adding rules for the quantifiers to
any adequate sequent calculus for the modal logic &lt;strong&gt;S5&lt;/strong&gt; allows for the derivation of the
Barcan formula&amp;mdash;$\diamondsuit\exists x\varphi \to \exists x \diamondsuit\varphi$. This
result is philosophically undesirable as, contra the Barcan Formula,  common-sense metaphysics would have it that things can possibly exist without actually existing. In this talk I give an
account of what is suspicious about such derivations by making use of a modal object
language with primitive scope indicators. Using this modal object language we see derivations of
the Barcan formula as requiring a certain kind of scope elision between &amp;ldquo;possibly, $a$ is $F$&amp;rdquo; (written in this
language as &amp;ldquo;$\diamondsuit\ a\ Fa$&amp;ldquo;) and &amp;ldquo;concerning $a$, possibly it is $F$&amp;rdquo; (written as &amp;ldquo;$a\
\diamondsuit Fa$&amp;ldquo;), where we are only able to infer &amp;ldquo;$\exists x \diamondsuit Fx$&amp;rdquo; from  the second
of these
formulas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More details are available on the event page on Sched &lt;a href=&#34;https://clmps2015.sched.org/event/264355f37ef212cef4a6d1af3eab0a6d&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/slides-handouts/hcfce-slides.pdf&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/slides-handouts/hcfce-handout.pdf&#34;&gt;Handout&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Barcan Formula, Necessary Existence and the Actuality Operator</title>
      <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/barcanactually/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 17:29:44 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/barcanactually/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the problems which those of us who believe that there are things which exist contingently (&lt;em&gt;Contingentists&lt;/em&gt; to use Timothy Williamson&amp;rsquo;s terminology) usually have with the Barcan Formula (=$\Diamond\exists x A \supset \exists x\Diamond A$) is that it somehow entails that everything which exists exists
necessarily. Usually this is demonstrated by appealing to the Converse Barcan Formula as well, which by itself already makes trouble for
the contingentist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might lead one to suspect that the Barcan
Formula is somehow &amp;lsquo;safe&amp;rsquo; so long as it doesn&amp;rsquo;t bring the Converse Barcan Formula with it. Particular instances may have odd consequence,
perhaps, but one might wonder whether it brings with it undesirable purely logical consequences. So long as its truth still allows that
there are &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; things which are contingent existents then perhaps all is well. As it happens, though, this position is untenable, as  as surely the contingentist
must reject the principle of &amp;lsquo;Necessary Actual Existence&amp;rsquo;
$$
(N@E):\quad \Box\forall x @ \exists y (x = y)
$$
That is, the principle that necessarily everything is actual. Unfortunately, this principle is derivable from the Barcan Formula in the logic of actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly we do need quite a bit of the logic of actually to do this, in particular we need to appeal to the schemata which is
characteristic of `real world&amp;rsquo; validity: $@A \equiv A$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assume $\Diamond \exists x \lnot @ \exists y ( x = y)$ for a reductio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the Barcan Formula we get $\exists x \Diamond\lnot @\exists y (x =y)$ by Modus Ponens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the principle that $\lnot @ A \equiv @\lnot A$ we get $\exists x \Diamond @\lnot\exists y (x =y)$ by the replacement of equivalents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the principle that $\Diamond @A \equiv @A$ we get $\exists x @\lnot\exists y (x =y)$ by the replacement of equivalents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the principle that $@A \equiv A$ we get $\exists x\lnot\exists y (x =y)$ by the replacement of equivalents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But in classical predicate logic we can derive $\lnot\exists x\lnot\exists y (x =y)$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So by reductio we can discharge our assumption and conclude $\lnot\Diamond \exists x \lnot @ \exists y ( x = y)$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So by principles valid in quantified &lt;strong&gt;K&lt;/strong&gt; we can finally conclude with $(N@E)$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some comments are worth making on this proof. In the logic of real-world validity replacement of equiavlents is not, in general, validity preserving. What the first few steps of the above proof show, though, is that $\exists x @\lnot\exists y (x =y)$ is generally valid. Then we can go from the instance of the real-world validity schema $@\lnot\exists y (x =y) \equiv \lnot\exists y(x = y)$ to
$\exists x(@\lnot\exists y (x =y) \equiv \lnot\exists y(x = y))$ by $(\exists I)$, which implies $\exists x@\lnot\exists y (x =y) \equiv \forall x\lnot\exists y(x = y))$, allowing us to conclude $\forall x\lnot\exists y(x = y)$ and (on the assumption that the domain is non-empty)
$\exists x\lnot\exists y(x = y)$ as desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even putting aside worries about us having to include some possibilia in our ontology,
in the presence of the logic of actually the Barcan Formula seems to commit us to the conclusion that in fact all possibilia are actual existents.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abstract for CLMPS</title>
      <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 16:45:53 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/abstract/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For those that (for some unknown reason) get their news about what&amp;rdquo;s happening
from this little corner of the internet, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://clmps.helsinki.fi/&#34;&gt;15th Congress on Logic, Methodology
and the Philosophy of Science&lt;/a&gt; is coming up in a few months, and today the
schedule and abstracts were posted on the website. As is common with many
things in this world we live in, lovely LaTeX was killed in the creation of
plaintext. To rectify this, for those that are interested, a loveingly MathML
rendered version of my abstract appears below the fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-hypersequent-calculus-for-contingent-existence-abstract:ac9d014eb02269a41f642e63c13d9dda&#34;&gt;A Hypersequent Calculus for Contingent Existence (Abstract)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is well known that the most straightforward way of adding rules for the quantifiers to any adequate sequent calculus for the modal logic
&lt;strong&gt;S5&lt;/strong&gt; allows for the derivation of the Barcan Formula&amp;mdash;$\diamondsuit\exists x\varphi \to \exists x \diamondsuit\varphi$. This result is
philosophically undesirably as, contra the Barcan Formula, common-sense metaphysics would have it that things can possibly exist without
actually existing. In this paper we give an account of what is
suspect about such derivations by making use of a modal object language with primitive scope indicators in which, in addition to their usual
&amp;ldquo;object denoting&amp;rdquo; role we also employ terms in a &amp;ldquo;scope indicating&amp;rdquo; capacity. Using this modal object language we can diagnose the
derivability of the Barcan formula in the standard language as arising out of the elision of a scope distinction between &amp;ldquo;possibly,
$a$ is $F$&amp;rdquo; (written in this language as &amp;ldquo;$\diamondsuit\ a\ Fa$&amp;ldquo;) and &amp;ldquo;concerning $a$, possibly it is $F$&amp;rdquo; (written as &amp;ldquo;$a\ \diamondsuit
Fa$&amp;ldquo;), where we are only able to infer &amp;ldquo;$\exists x \diamondsuit Fx$&amp;rdquo; from  the second of these formulas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to manipulate this object language we make use of &amp;ldquo;importation&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;exportation&amp;rdquo; rules which govern the movement of scope indicators
in addition to more standard left- and right-insertion rules. Furthermore, we also make use of a distinction between rules which
introduce a context into which we can quantify, and those which (prior to the use of importation/exportation rules) we cannot&amp;mdash;the rules for
negation and the modal operators being of this second kind. The resultant
modal hypersequent calculi provided is sound and complete w.r.t. first-order Kripke models with non-constant domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently I&amp;rsquo;m on in the 11:00-13:00 session on the 5th of August, in a great session on modal logic and mereology with Volker Halbach, Peter Fritz, and Hsing-chien Tsai&amp;mdash;so come along to see them, and see me talk about hypersequents and quantification for free :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urn Logic, Quantification and Modal Logic</title>
      <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/urn-logic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 20:07:56 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/urn-logic/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;One of the great pleasures of doing logic is finding problems in one area which can be solved using the techniques and
insights from another. What I want to briefly mention here is a neat example of this involving an interesting approach
to quantificational logic due to Veikko Rantala called &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00558760&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Urn Logic&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;. The core idea behind urn logic&amp;rsquo;s semantics for the
quantifiers is that the objects which the quantifiers range over can vary over the course of the evaluation of a formula,
depending on which objects are selected from the domain by earlier quantifiers. Veikko&amp;rsquo;s original semantics for this is
in the style of Hintikka&amp;rsquo;s game theoretic semantics, and I&amp;rsquo;ve proposed a more standard version of the semantics in my
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/urn-logic.pdf&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;A Sequent Calculus for Urn Logic&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;. What I&amp;rsquo;m interested in here, though, is a &amp;lsquo;classical&amp;rsquo; semantics for Urn Logic proposed
by Max Cresswell, and how a question he asks about the expressivity of this semantics can be answered using a very familiar
construction from modal logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cresswell-s-classical-exposition:e11132a276315be53ce9adcebdd68daf&#34;&gt;Cresswell&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Classical Exposition&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cresswell&amp;rsquo;s semantics for Urn logic, which he articulates in his excellent paper
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00370339&#34;&gt;Urn Models: A Classical Exposition&lt;/a&gt;, are as follows. A model is a triple
$\langle A, D, V\rangle$, with $A$ being a set of individuals (approximately, our initial domain), and $V$ an assignment
of extensions to predicate letters (done in the usual manner). All the action in the semantics concerns $D$, which is
a function from sequences of objects from $A$ to subsets of $A$. We also change the recursive clause for the quantifiers
as follows
$$
\langle A, D, V\rangle\models \forall x \varphi[s] \iff \langle A, D, V\rangle\models \varphi[s&amp;rsquo;]
$$&lt;br /&gt;
where $s&amp;rsquo;$ is an $x$-variant of $s$ s.t. $s&amp;rsquo;(x)\in D(\langle s(x_{1}), \ldots, s(x_{n})\rangle)$ where
$x_{1}, \ldots, x_{n}$ are the free-variables in $\forall x\varphi$. For convenience (so that we don&amp;rsquo;t have to make
some kind of choice concerning the order of the free-variables in formulas) we also need to impose the constraint that
$D(\langle a_{1}, \ldots, a_{n}\rangle) = D(\langle b{1}, \ldots, b{n}\rangle)$ whenever $b{1}, \ldots, b{n}$ is a
permutation of $a_{1}, \ldots, a_{n}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we&amp;rsquo;re going to focus on here is a constraint on Urn Models which Cresswell singles out in the course of his completeness
proof, which we&amp;rsquo;ll call (Dist.) (in Cresswell&amp;rsquo;s paper it appears as &lt;strong&gt;4.3&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Dist.) If $b \in D(\langle a_{1}, \ldots, a_{n}\rangle)$ then $b$ is distinct from each $a_{1}, \ldots, a_{n}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerning this condition Cresswell has the following to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;The satisfaction of [(Dist.)] is interesting because it is not a condition one
would want to put on all urn models. This means that there would seem to
be no formula which entails that&lt;/em&gt; $a_{i} \in D(\langle a_{1}, \ldots, a_{n}\rangle)$ &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; $1 \leq i \leq n$.&amp;rdquo;
(Cresswell 1982, p.121)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cresswell is indeed right that (Dist.) is not a condition we want to place on all our urn models. As it happens, though, placing this
constraint on our models doesn&amp;rsquo;t make a difference to the validities of the logic as, given a model $\mathcal{M}$ which doesn&amp;rsquo;t
satisfy (Dist.) we can always construct a model $\mathcal{M^{d}}$ so that for every $\mathcal{M}$-assignment, there is a
$\mathcal{M^{d}}$-assignment s.t. $\mathcal{M}$ and $\mathcal{M^{d}}$ agree on which formulas are satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate this we just need to use a construction which is reminiscient of the &amp;lsquo;unravelling&amp;rsquo; construction which is often used
to show that the class of all irreflexive frames is not modally definable&amp;mdash;which is not entirely surprising, considering the
extent to which (Dist.) looks like a combination of irreflexivity and antisymmetry on our &amp;lsquo;accessibility relation&amp;rsquo;. The construction
is relatively simple. First let us establish some notation. Given a sequence $s$ and a sequence $s&amp;rsquo;$ let $s\ast s&amp;rsquo;$ be the
concatenation of $s$ and $s&amp;rsquo;$, similarly given an object $a$ let $s\ast a$ be the result of concatenating $a$ to the end of $s$. Given a sequence of sequences $s = \langle s_{1}, \ldots, s_{n}\rangle$ say that $s_{i}$ is the maximal element of $s$ iff $s{i}$ is the longest member of $s$. Finally, given a sequence $s$ let $s^{l}$ be the final element of $s$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-construction:e11132a276315be53ce9adcebdd68daf&#34;&gt;The Construction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose that $\mathcal{M} = \langle A, D, V\rangle$ is an urn model. Let $\mathcal{M}^{d} = \langle A^{d}, D^{d}, V^{d}\rangle$ be defined as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$A^{d}$ is the set of all sequences $\langle a_{1}, \ldots, a_{n}$ of elements from $A$ where $a_{n}\in D(\langle a_{1}, \ldots, a_{n-1}\rangle)$ (with $\langle a_{1}\rangle\in A^{d}$ iff $a_{1}\in D(\emptyset)$)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$D^{d}(\emptyset) = D(\emptyset)$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$s \in D^{d}(a_{1}, \ldots, a_{n})$ iff $s= a_{i}\ast b$ for some $b\in A$, where $a_{i}$ is the maximal element of $\langle a_{1}, \ldots, a_{n}\rangle$ and $b\in D(a_{i})$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$V^{d}(F) = {\langle s_{1}, \ldots, s_{n}\rangle | \langle s_{1}^{l}, \ldots s_{n}^{l}\rangle \in V(F)}$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be fairly obvious to see that $\mathcal{M}^{d}$ is an urn model (all we need to do is check that it satisfies the permutation condition). Readers who are familiar with the model theory for modal logic will notice the striking resemblence between this model
construction and the &lt;em&gt;unravelling&lt;/em&gt; construction (due, to the best of my knowledge, to either Henrik Sahlqvist or M. Dummett and E.J. Lemmon) which we can use to show (for example) that the smallest normal modal logic &lt;strong&gt;K&lt;/strong&gt; is
determined by the class of all trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given urn models $\mathcal{M}$ and $\mathcal{M}^{d}$ let us say that a $\mathcal{M}^{d}$-assignment $s&amp;rsquo;$ is &lt;em&gt;safe relative to&lt;/em&gt; $x1, \ldots xn$
for a $\mathcal{M}$-assignment $s$ if and only if there is a sequence $\langle s{1}, \ldots, s{n-1}\rangle$ of length $n-1$ constructed out of
$s(x_{i})$ ($1\leq i \leq n$), and some ordering $\langle a_{x_1}, \ldots, a_{x_n}\rangle$ of $x_{1}, \ldots, x_{n}$,  $s&amp;rsquo;(a_{x_i})=\langle s{1}, \ldots, s{i-1}\rangle \ast\langle s(a_{x_i})\rangle$. Approximately speaking assignments which are safe relative
to some variables are ones where the values assigned to those variables could have come from some sequence of legal selections of objects from
our model. With this in hand we can then prove that, for all urn models $\mathcal{M}$, assignments $s$ and formulas $\varphi$ we have
$$
\mathcal{M}\models\varphi[s] \iff \mathcal{M}^{d}\models\varphi[s&amp;rsquo;]
$$
where $s&amp;rsquo;$ is safe relative to the free-variables in $\varphi$ for $s$. Given that the condition that $s&amp;rsquo;$ be safe relative to
the free-variables in $\varphi$ for $s$ is vacuously satisfied in the case where $\varphi$ is a sentence we can quite easily conclude
that there is no &lt;em&gt;sentence&lt;/em&gt; which is true in precisely those urn models in which for all $n$ we have $a_{i} \in D(\langle a_{1}, \ldots, a_{n}\rangle)$ for $1 \leq i \leq n$.  In order to show that there is no such formula of any kind we would need to show that for every
set of variables $x_1, \ldots x_{n}$ and $\mathcal{M}$-assignment $s$ there is a $\mathcal{M}^{d}$-assignment $s&amp;rsquo;$ which is safe
for $x_1, \ldots x_{n}$. In the great tradition of leaving unknowns as exercises, I leave this as an exercise to the reader.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introductions</title>
      <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/introductions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2015 04:35:45 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/introductions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello! Welcome to this, the website of Rohan French, Australian philosophical logician at large in Europe. I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to put this site together for some time, and was recently inspired by the redesign of Greg Restall&amp;rsquo;s wonderful &lt;a href=&#34;http://consequently.org&#34;&gt;consequently.org&lt;/a&gt;, and how pleasant (for a tinkerer who briefly worked as a web developer) &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; was to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope is that this won&amp;rsquo;t just be another repository for pre-prints of publications, like many academic websites are. That&amp;rsquo;s not to say that such sites are bad, mind you, but (vanity aside) I could simply do that using a google site. What I want to do here is to &lt;em&gt;not just&lt;/em&gt; store pre-prints (and drafts) of my papers here, but also share various thoughts and results which are perhaps not immediately destined for publication&amp;mdash;such as  minor technical results, or thoughts on papers. Hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll also eventually talk a bit about some of the small python programs I put together to create some of the assessment for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/logic1&#34;&gt;Logic: Language and Information 1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/logic2&#34;&gt;Logic: Langauge and Information 2&lt;/a&gt;, and how they might be helpful in face-to-face teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More things will slowly start appearing here over the coming days, but for the time being here&amp;rsquo;s a brief description of what you&amp;rsquo;ll currently find around here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Here you can find pre-prints of my published papers, as well as links to the official versions. Some unpublished or work-in-progress papers will probably appear here soon, too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/about/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If you&amp;rsquo;ve read this far and you have no-idea who I am, or you&amp;rsquo;ve read the station-identification at the bottom of the page and are curious to know more about this terribly interesting seeming person, then you can find some of what you want to know here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/post/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Archive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Here you&amp;rsquo;ll find a list of all the posts (like the one you&amp;rsquo;re reading) that&amp;rsquo;ve been posted here. At the moment this is probably not going to be the most interesting page on this site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the time being, you can also find me on twitter at &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/RohanFrench&#34;&gt;@RohanFrench&lt;/a&gt;, or email me at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:rohan.french@gmail.com&#34;&gt;rohan.french@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rohan-french.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=image-left style=&#34;width:300px; border:1px solid #e0e3e5;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/images/rohan-descartes.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;With Descartes at Versailles circa 2015.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;span class=&#34;illuminate&#34;&gt;Dr. Rohan French&lt;/span&gt;.
I did my PhD at Monash University in Australia under watchful eyes
of Lloyd Humberstone, working on translations between modal logics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2013-2014 I worked with Greg Restall and Jen Davoren on turning the University of
Melbourne&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate logic course into a MOOC on Coursera, resulting in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/logic1&#34;&gt;Logic: Language and Information 1&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/logic2&#34;&gt;Logic: Language and Information 2&lt;/a&gt;.
One day I&amp;rsquo;ll probably put some of the Python programs I developed to put together
the continuous assessment for the subject online here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently I&amp;rsquo;m in the Netherlands where I&amp;rsquo;m working with Associate Professor Catarina Dutilh Novaes
on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/therootsofdeduction/&#34;&gt;Roots of Deduction&lt;/a&gt; project at the University of Groningen, where I&amp;rsquo;m working on connections between proof-theory and dialogue games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research is focused on issues in &lt;em&gt;philosophical logic&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;philosophy of logic&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m
particularly interested in issues concerning philosophical proof-theory (esp. proof-theory
for weak quantificational logics, modal logics and varieties of inferentialism), modal logic
(esp. first- and higher-order modal logics, and issues involving expressive power),
translations between logics, and issues involving substructural logics. I&amp;rsquo;m generally interested in
any area of philosophy where formal methods can be fruitfully applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;m not doing research I usually spend my time reading science-fiction and fantasy
novels, listening to music and playing computer games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drink &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of coffee. I recomend &lt;a href=&#34;http://blackandbloom.nl/&#34;&gt;Black &amp;amp; Bloom&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;rsquo;re in Groningen, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://marketlane.com.au/&#34;&gt;Market Lane Coffee&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;rsquo;re in Melbourne.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curriculum Vitae</title>
      <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rohan-french.github.io/cv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here you can find a copy of my &lt;span class=&#34;badge&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=_blank href=&#34;Rohan French CV.pdf&#34;&gt;CV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;All PDFs here are authors preprints. To get the official version follow the
&lt;span class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;[doi]&lt;/span&gt; link where available. All publications are listed in
descending order by year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;single-author-publications:a65cffa9c73225e9b2db0699034df561&#34;&gt;Single Author Publications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Sequent Calculus for Urn Logic&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Logic, Language and Information&lt;/em&gt; 24 (2015), 131-147.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/urn-logic.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10849-015-9216-5&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;[doi]&lt;/a&gt;(Open Access)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the Mood for &lt;strong&gt;S4&lt;/strong&gt;: The Expressive Power of the Subjunctive Modal Language in Weak Background Logics&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Studia Logica&lt;/em&gt; 103 (2015), 239-263.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/itmfs4.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007%2Fs11225-014-9557-0&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;[doi]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Expressive Power, Mood, and Actuality&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Synthese&lt;/em&gt; 190 (2013), 1689-1699.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/epmaac.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11229-011-9933-5&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;[doi]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Denumerably Many Post-Complete Normal Modal Logics with Propositional Constants&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Notre Dame Journal of Formal Logic&lt;/em&gt; 53 (2012), 549-556.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/dmpcnmlpc.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1215/00294527-1722746&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;[doi]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;An Argument against General Validity?&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Thought&lt;/em&gt; 1 (2012), 4-9.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/aagv.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/tht3.1&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;[doi]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Simplified Embedding of &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt; into Monomodal &lt;strong&gt;K&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Logic Journal of the IGPL&lt;/em&gt; 17 (2009), 421-428.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/aseEinK.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jigpal/jzp024&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;[doi]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Note on the Logic of Eventual Permanence for Linear Time&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Notre Dame Journal of Formal Logic&lt;/em&gt; 49 (2008), 137-142.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1215/00294527-2008-003&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;[doi]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;co-authored-publications:a65cffa9c73225e9b2db0699034df561&#34;&gt;Co-Authored Publications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;(with Lloyd Humberstone) &amp;ldquo;An Observation Concerning Porte&amp;rsquo;s Rule in Modal Logic&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Bulletin of the Section of Logic&lt;/em&gt; 44:1 / 2 (2015), 25-31.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/porte.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;(with  Dave Ripley) &amp;ldquo;Contractions of Noncontractive Consequence Relations&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Review of Symbolic Logic&lt;/em&gt; (forthcoming)
&lt;a href=&#34;http://philpapers.org/archive/FRECON.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S1755020314000409&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;[doi]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;(with Lloyd Humberstone) &amp;ldquo;Partial Confirmation of a Conjecture on the Boxdot Translation in Modal Logic&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Australasian Journal of Logic&lt;/em&gt; 7 (2009), 56-61.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ojs.victoria.ac.nz/ajl/article/view/1808&#34; class=badge-small&gt;Available Online from the AJL.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reviews:a65cffa9c73225e9b2db0699034df561&#34;&gt;Reviews&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Review of A.A. Rini and M. J. Cresswell &amp;lsquo;The World-Time Parallel&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;Australasian Journal of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;, 92, (2014), 802-805.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/wtp-review.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00048402.2014.887738&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;[doi]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;unpublished:a65cffa9c73225e9b2db0699034df561&#34;&gt;Unpublished&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Translational Embeddings in Modal Logic&lt;/em&gt;, PhD Thesis, Monash University.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rohan-french.github.io/writing/phd-thesis.pdf&#34; class=&#34;badge badge-small&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-file-pdf-o&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>