<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conferences on Rohan French: Logician at Large</title>
    <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/categories/conferences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conferences on Rohan French: Logician at Large</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 16:45:53 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://rohan-french.github.io/categories/conferences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Abstract for CLMPS</title>
      <link>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 16:45:53 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rohan-french.github.io/post/abstract/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For those that (for some unknown reason) get their news about what&amp;rdquo;s happening
from this little corner of the internet, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://clmps.helsinki.fi/&#34;&gt;15th Congress on Logic, Methodology
and the Philosophy of Science&lt;/a&gt; is coming up in a few months, and today the
schedule and abstracts were posted on the website. As is common with many
things in this world we live in, lovely LaTeX was killed in the creation of
plaintext. To rectify this, for those that are interested, a loveingly MathML
rendered version of my abstract appears below the fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-hypersequent-calculus-for-contingent-existence-abstract:ac9d014eb02269a41f642e63c13d9dda&#34;&gt;A Hypersequent Calculus for Contingent Existence (Abstract)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is well known that the most straightforward way of adding rules for the quantifiers to any adequate sequent calculus for the modal logic
&lt;strong&gt;S5&lt;/strong&gt; allows for the derivation of the Barcan Formula&amp;mdash;$\diamondsuit\exists x\varphi \to \exists x \diamondsuit\varphi$. This result is
philosophically undesirably as, contra the Barcan Formula, common-sense metaphysics would have it that things can possibly exist without
actually existing. In this paper we give an account of what is
suspect about such derivations by making use of a modal object language with primitive scope indicators in which, in addition to their usual
&amp;ldquo;object denoting&amp;rdquo; role we also employ terms in a &amp;ldquo;scope indicating&amp;rdquo; capacity. Using this modal object language we can diagnose the
derivability of the Barcan formula in the standard language as arising out of the elision of a scope distinction between &amp;ldquo;possibly,
$a$ is $F$&amp;rdquo; (written in this language as &amp;ldquo;$\diamondsuit\ a\ Fa$&amp;ldquo;) and &amp;ldquo;concerning $a$, possibly it is $F$&amp;rdquo; (written as &amp;ldquo;$a\ \diamondsuit
Fa$&amp;ldquo;), where we are only able to infer &amp;ldquo;$\exists x \diamondsuit Fx$&amp;rdquo; from  the second of these formulas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to manipulate this object language we make use of &amp;ldquo;importation&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;exportation&amp;rdquo; rules which govern the movement of scope indicators
in addition to more standard left- and right-insertion rules. Furthermore, we also make use of a distinction between rules which
introduce a context into which we can quantify, and those which (prior to the use of importation/exportation rules) we cannot&amp;mdash;the rules for
negation and the modal operators being of this second kind. The resultant
modal hypersequent calculi provided is sound and complete w.r.t. first-order Kripke models with non-constant domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently I&amp;rsquo;m on in the 11:00-13:00 session on the 15th of August, in a great session on modal logic and mereology with Volker Halbach, Peter Fritz, and Hsing-chien Tsai&amp;mdash;so come along to see them, and see me talk about hypersequents and quantification for free :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>